Hello everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco and my name is
Catherine and today we've got a
great lesson for you about traveling and
getting directions. That's right so sometimes
we are looking for an address, we are
looking for our friend's house and we
can't find it so what do you have to do?
You have to stop and ask someone for
directions. There's actually a joke in many
countries that men hate to ask for directions
and so this is the women's approach
asking and getting directions and finally
finding your way. So it's a good thing.
That's a very good thing. So we're
gonna jump right into the dialogue.
Let's see what happens here and if
they can find the place you're looking for.
We've been going around in circles for the
past hour. Will you just please stop and
ask for directions? We are not lost.
I'm just taking the scenic route. Yeah
whatever. I told you we should buy that
GPS that was on sale but would you listen
to me? No this is so typical. Fine.
I'll ask this guy for directions if it will
shut your trap. Excuse me sir can you
tell me how to get to St. Mary's Church?
Sure go down park road, turn left,
go up as far as the set of traffic lights
and turn left. The place you're looking
for is the second building on the right.
Thanks. See was that
hard? If you would only
listen to me more often
you would be better off.
All right we're back so well the woman
was obviously a little bit angry that the
guy refused to admit that he was lost.
That's right she's very frustrated and
this has been in movies and in books
and all sorts of things. This kind of
story of the man not wanting to ask
for directions and so he keeps saying
listen I've got these excuses. I'm
taking the scenic route for example. That's
right and that's our first word for today
on language take away. Language take away.
So as you say the scenic route what
does he mean by that? Okay route is
like a path or a trail or kind of like
the way that you go somewhere. So the
routes to my house but in this case the
scenic route or the scenic route you can
say in both ways is the most beautiful
way to go. It's a little bit longer.
The longer one. Yeah so you can say oh
it's just the scenic route. It's not really
true it's just the longer route. Right
exactly. So that's the excuse that he's
giving her is like no I'm not lost
we're taking longer because well we're
taking the beautiful route. All right
with all the trees and the animal in the
lakes. No I don't buy it. I don't believe
this. That's right and she said yeah
whatever you know what we need a GPS.
Okay GPS global positioning system so
many people have these in their cars
these days. This is like a an electronic
map that will use your location to
show you where to go. It's very useful
and especially in places like the
United States that have streets that are
clearly marked and it's just a little
bit easier to get around. You know you
can just get in your car type in the
address you want to go to and the thing
talks to you is it's turn left to go
straight turn right. Creepy. So this is a
very useful device. It's like a computer
that you use in your computer. A GPS.
All right so she's talking about the
GPS and then at the end of that line she
says this is so typical. So what getting
lost. All right getting lost it's so
typical. So something that is typical
is common. This is so normal. This is so
typical. This is so something you normally
do. So what other examples could we
give with the word typical? Something
that is typical. Okay well you can have a
behavior like this. What he did was
typical. We can also say in my typical
Saturday I wake up late and drink
a coffee and take a nap. Okay cool.
So it's common. It's regular. It's frequent
maybe. That's right. Or you know you go
at the dinner and your friend is late.
You say oh this is so typical of him.
Right he's always late. Very good.
All right and we have one last set of words
here and when the guy was giving him
instructions he said you know what? Go
left go right whatever and then he said
until you reach the set of traffic lights.
So what is a traffic light? Well you
know what a light is. You know a traffic is
traffic is cars driving on the road.
Trucks things like that. So traffic light
is a special light with three colors.
Red, yellow and green. And it tells you if
you can stop or go. So they're also
called stop lights. That's right. Okay so
stop lights and traffic lights is the
same thing. Usually they hang from above
this street. Okay very good. Words and
phrases there. Why don't we listen to our
dialogue again and we'll
be back in just a little bit.
We've been going around in circles for the
past hour. Will you just please stop and
ask for directions? We are not
lost. I'm just taking the scenic route.
Yeah whatever. I told you we should buy
that GPS that was on sale. But would you
listen to me? No, this is so typical.
Fine. I'll ask this guy for directions if
it will shut your trap. Excuse me sir,
can you tell me how to get to St. Mary's
Church? Sure. Go down park road, turn
left, go up as far as the set of traffic
lights and turn left. The place you're
looking for is the second building on the
right. Thanks. See was that hard? If you
would only listen to me more often you
would be better off. All right, so we've
got some great phrases coming up in
fluency builder. Fluency builder. So the
first phrase that we're going to look at
is what the wife said at the very beginning
she said we have been going around
in circles for the past hour. Going
around in circles. So we could say we've
been driving in circles. In circles means
you've been making the same route
over and over and over again. You keep
seeing the same house, the same tree, the
same house, the same tree. So this means
we're not going anywhere. You could also
say Marco, I wish you had brought the map.
We've been walking in circles for
two hours. Okay, so you can use it if
you're driving or if you're walking in any
situation like that. Exactly. Okay, good.
All right, so going around in circles.
Now, moving on the guy was a little bit
irritated with her and he said something
that's a little bit in place. He said,
you know what, I'm going to ask for
directions if it will shut your trap. In
polite, this is rude. This is rude. Yeah,
this is very rude. So be careful when
you use this. You can say, hey, shut your
trap. Okay, so shut
means to close, but trap.
This is your mouth.
Okay, your mouth is a trap.
It's kind of like a trap. In this case,
shut your trap is a set phrase and
it means shut up. Be quiet. Stop talking.
So how can we say this in a nicer way?
For example, I've heard people say, your
yap, shut your yap. Yeah, shut your yapper.
I would say, can you please stop talking?
Or can we have some quiet time now? Can we
have some quiet time? Yeah, that's a polite
way. The rude way is shut up. Shut up.
Yeah, shut your mouth.
That's very direct, though, right?
Very rude. Yeah, that's right.
Okay, so shut your
trap. Shut your trap.
And then the wife said, well, see,
there you go. We got directions.
We're going to get there now. And
was that hard? If you would only listen
to me more often,
you would be better off.
So the guy would be better off.
That doesn't really make
much sense to be better off.
Okay, so you have to
think of this as a phrase,
not about the individual
words to be better
off means to be happier
or in some way better.
So for example, if I earned
more money, I think I'd be
better off. Okay, okay, I
have a nicer like to be happier.
Maybe more successful. Right.
Or if you only listened to me,
you would be better off
means you would make
better decisions. You
would have a better situation.
So I could say, if she got a divorce,
she would be better off. That's right.
Her life would improve.
Her life wouldn't
improve to be better
off. This is a great, great,
very useful phrase. Very useful. All right.
So why don't we listen to the dialogue for
the very last time and we'll be
back to talk a little bit more with you.
We've been going around
in circles for the past hour.
Will you just please stop
and ask for directions?
We are not lost.
I'm just taking the scenic
route. Yeah, whatever.
I told you we should buy
that GPS that was on sale.
But would you listen to
me? No, this is so typical.
Fine. I'll ask this guy for directions if
it will shut your trap. Excuse me, sir.
Can you tell me how to
get to St. Mary's Church?
Sure. Go down, park
road, turn left, go
up as far as the set of
traffic lights and turn left.
The place you're
looking for is the
second building on the right. Thanks. See,
was that hard? If you would only listen to
me more often, you would be better off. All
right. So the whole thing about men asking
for directions. Why
do you think men don't
like to ask for directions?
Well, it depends on the person.
But I think a lot of people don't like
to admit that they don't know. Okay,
because if you ask for directions, it means
I don't know where I'm going. I need help.
So this is one problem. The other
problem is sometimes directions are bad.
I think so too. Sometimes when you receive
an invitation or instructions on how to get
to someone's house,
they're very ambiguous.
They're like, you know,
you pass the dog that's
sitting at the corner and
you're like, there's no duck, what?
How? Yeah, I know.
I know someone who
lives in Costa Rica and her
address is go down the
main street and take the
second left after the post office and after
that take the right after the general store
and 400 paces is the
house. So there's no address.
There's no address. It's, you know, so
these instructions can be very confusing,
very vague like you
said. So I think there's
a couple different problems. I also heard
a joke the other day about kid ask his
mom. He said, hey, why was Moses leading
everyone through the desert for 40 years?
And she's like, because he
refused to ask for directions.
Funny. I like that. I was going to say
why because he's going into circles.
All right. So if you have
any questions about
today's lessons or
comments, maybe you can
tell us, do you like
to ask for directions or
do you like to figure things out alone?
Let us know on our website, EnglishPod.com.
All right. We'll see you guys there.
Bye. Bye.